Programming models are fundamental specifications that define
プログラミングモデルとは、定義を行う基本的な仕様です
how software is structured
ソフトウェアの構造
and executed they provide a framework
と実行方法を定め、フレームワークを提供します
for developers to express all gritters
開発者がアルゴリズムを表現するための
and organise cold often obstructing away low level details
コードを整理するためのもので、低レベルの詳細を抽象化します
of the underlying hardware or execution well
基盤となるハードウェアや実行環境の
different models are suited to different types of problems
さまざまなモデルは、異なる種類の問題に適しています
and hardware detectors offering
ハードウェアアーキテクチャもさまざまで
varying levels of obstructions
抽象化のレベルも異なります
and control in this chapter
この章では
will review quantum and classical programming models
量子と古典のプログラミングモデルを見ていきます
and see how we can combine them to operate all greater
そしてそれらを組み合わせてアルゴリズムを実行する方法を確認します
in hi
ハイブリッド環境で
will start with the programming model
まずはプログラミングモデルから始めましょう
for a quantum computer one fundamental programming model
量子コンピュータ向けの基本的なプログラミングモデルとして
which is familiar to almost all quantum developers
ほぼすべての量子開発者に馴染みのある
is the quantum circuit we won't go
quantum circuitがあります。詳細には立ち入りません
into the detail of quantum circuits
quantum circuitの詳細については
here as we already have many great resources
すでに多くの優れたリソースがあるためです
including a lecture by joan waters
Joan Watersによる講義も含まれています
will only mention that the circuit is built out of
ここでは、circuitがワイヤーと呼ばれる線で構成されており
a set of lines called wires which represent cubits
qubitを表すことだけ触れておきます
as well as gates which represent operation on quantum states
また、量子状態への操作を表すgateと
and a set of measurements
測定のセットがあります
another important programming model concept
もう一つの重要なプログラミングモデルの概念は
for
primitiveです
this primitives represent the most popular tasks
primitiveは、量子コンピュータで最もよく使われるタスクを表します
that users tried to accomplish with the quantum computer
ユーザーが量子コンピュータで実現しようとする
there are two primitives available at this moment
現在、2つのprimitiveが利用可能です
simpler and estimator simpler gives you the ability
SamplerとEstimatorです。Samplerは
to sample a state prepared by quantum circuit
quantum circuitで準備した状態をサンプリングできます
and estimator lets you estimate the expectation value of
Estimatorは、期待値を推定できます
an observable for a system in the state prepared by your quantum
observableの期待値を、量子circuitで準備した状態について
circuit the final concept
circuitの最後の概念として
we're going to talk about in this section
このセクションで取り上げるのは
is transportation transportation
transpilationです。transpilation
is the process of writing a give it input circuit
とは、入力されたcircuitを変換するプロセスで
to much the apology of a specific quantum
特定の量子デバイスのトポロジーに合わせます
device
デバイス上での実行のために
for execution on noisy quantity computers
ノイズのある量子コンピュータでの実行向けに
similar to classical compilers
古典コンパイラと同様に
a transcallation routine gradually changes
transpilerのルーティンは段階的に
the structure of the circuit by a playing set of passes
circuitの構造を変換します。一連のpassを適用することで
now let's talk about classical programming models
では、古典のプログラミングモデルについて話しましょう
there many programming models
古典コンピュータには多くのプログラミングモデルがありますが
for classical computers
古典コンピュータ向けの
but in this chapter will focus on to
この章では2つに絞って説明します
the boss popular parallel programming
最もよく使われる並列プログラミングと
and task workforce by using this two models
タスクワークフローです。この2つのモデルを使うことで
incombination with quantum programming models
量子プログラミングモデルと組み合わせることで
one can express pretty much any hybrid
あらゆるハイブリッドを表現できます
quantum classical workflow of any complexity
どんな複雑さの量子古典ワークフローでも
the better programming model
並列プログラミングモデルは
divides a program into some problems that can be executed
プログラムを同時に実行できるサブ問題に分割します
at the same time there are two main paradigms of parallel programming
並列プログラミングには2つの主なパラダイムがあります
shared memory perilism and distributed memory paralysm
共有メモリ並列処理と分散メモリ並列処理です
for our purposes here let's focus on distributed memory model
ここでは分散メモリモデルに焦点を当てましょう
a distributed memory model
分散メモリモデルは
uses independent processes on separate course
独立したプロセスを別々のコアで実行します
or notes where each process has its own memory
またはノードで、各プロセスは独自のメモリを持ちます
and communication happens using message passing there
通信はメッセージパッシングで行われます
a few concepts that will be useful to know
知っておくと便利な概念がいくつかあります
the first is the process
最初はプロセスです
which is independent instance of the program
別々のコアで実行されるプログラムの独立したインスタンスです
running on a separate core
別々のコアで動作します
also the rank which is a unique identify of the process
次にランクです。プロセスの一意な識別子です
and then there is single program
そして、単一プログラム
multiple data obstruction model
複数データという抽象化モデルがあります
which is an obstruction model
これは抽象化モデルで
for computation where a single instance of the program
プログラムの単一インスタンスが複数のノードに配布される計算です
is distributed to multiple notes
複数のノードに分散されます
so the source code is the same
ソースコードは同じですが
but the date on those notes are different
各ノードのデータは異なります
the execution and peril programming model
並列プログラミングモデルでの実行は
happens in the following way
以下のように行われます
a single program distributes to multiple notes
単一プログラムが複数のノードに配布され
and starts multiple parallel processes
複数の並列プロセスが開始されます
the control for of the program is dictated by the rank
プログラムの制御フローはランクによって決まります
or the identifier of the process
つまり、プロセスの識別子によって
and communication happens
通信は
through message passing
メッセージパッシングを通じて行われます
a task workful programming model
タスクワークフロープログラミングモデルは
obstruct computation intergraph or deck
計算をグラフまたはDAGとして抽象化します
where each note of the graph is a particular task
グラフの各ノードは特定のタスクです
or job and edges of dependencies data
またはジョブで、エッジは依存関係やデータを示します
and ordering examples can be found in our documentation
具体的な例はドキュメントに記載されています
after all the sequence that we're always talking about in quantum
量子コンピューティングでよく語られる一連の処理
computing mapping optimisation
マッピング、最適化
execution and post processing
実行、後処理は
is a task workful programming model
タスクワークフロープログラミングモデルです
where all tasks are executed one after
すべてのタスクが順番に実行されます
another in the pipeline
パイプラインの中で一つずつ
but with task workflows
ただしタスクワークフローでは
we're not bound to sequential execution order
順次実行に縛られることはありません
and can execute tasks in parallel
タスクを並列で実行することもできます
each task or work flow can be an entire parallel job
各タスクやワークフローは、それ自体が並列ジョブになれます
of its own so you can mix
ですから、これらのモデルを組み合わせて
and match this models to describe all greater
任意のアルゴリズムを記述できます
of any complexity.
どんな複雑さのものでも。
Let's try applying some of the concepts that we learn
学んだ概念をコードに適用してみましょう
to cold first will try to run simple hello world
まず、並列プログラミングパラダイムを使ってシンプルな Hello World を試します
using parallel programming paradigm
並列プログラミングのパラダイムを使って
we're gonna be using open mpi
Open MPIを使用します
which is the implementation of npi protocol
これはMPIプロトコルの実装で
which is the sender for message passing
並列プログラミングにおける
in parallel programming
メッセージパッシングの標準です
first we need to have our program regime
まず、プログラムを用意する必要があります
here where using mpi for by
ここでは mpi4py を使っています
which is bite and binding
PythonのバインディングMPIです
for npi and as you can see where using ground here to decide
MPIのPythonバインディングで、ランクを使ってプログラムの
the control flow of the program
制御フローを決めているのがわかります
so let's check our submission script.
では、サブミッションスクリプトを確認しましょう。
As you can see we're gonna be using two notes
2つのノードを使用する設定になっています
one task per note in normal partition
normalパーティションでノードあたり1タスク
and let's crown our program we're gonna moit a bit
プログラムを実行してみます。少し待って
and we can check results of our job
ジョブの結果を確認できます
as you can see who have log outputs of our program
プログラムのログ出力が確認できます
here we use two notes and two processes
2つのノードと2つのプロセスを使っています
which are identified by a rank
ランクで識別されます
as you can see here as an output
出力を見るとわかるように
rank zero in frank one which used to decide
ランク0とランク1が制御フローを決めています
the control floor of our program
プログラムの制御フローを決定します
is you can see ring zero process sent
ランク0のプロセスが送信したのがわかります
some pay load to the rank one process
ランク1のプロセスへのペイロードを
and rank one process accepted
ランク1のプロセスがそれを受信しました
dispay who also talk about task war force
次にタスクワークフローについても説明します
there are tools that called work
ワークロード管理システムと呼ばれる
for management systems they're specifically designed
ツールがあります。これらは特別に設計されており
to run complex workforce
複雑なワークフローを実行するためのものです
but to not overload you were going to be using built in
ただし、複雑にしすぎないよう、Slurmの組み込み
dependency feature in slow
依存関係機能を使います
to construct those computational groups
計算グループを構築するために
first we need to have tasks of power work
まず、ワークフローのタスクを用意します
for ready this is the same cold
これは同じコードです
the benefit of having each of this tasks
各タスクを分けることのメリットは
as mapping optimisation execution
マッピング、最適化、実行
post process as a separate steps
後処理を別々のステップとして持てることです
is that we can specify unique resource requirements
各タスクに固有のリソース要件を指定できます
for each of the tasks for example mapping optimisation
例えば、マッピング、最適化
postposing does not need
後処理は必要ありません
access to quantity resources
量子リソースへのアクセスが
therefore we can run them on classical partition.
そのため、古典パーティションで実行できます。
But execution task will need
一方、実行タスクには
quantity resources therefore we're going to run it on quantity
量子リソースが必要なため、量子
partition.
パーティションで実行します。
Let's now you slearn dependency feature to chain tasks
依存関係機能を使ってタスクを繋いでみましょう
into warflow.
ワークフローに連結します。
As you can see was still running
まだ実行中です
our as better comment with flag possible
sbatchコマンドに--parsableフラグをつけて実行し
which will return the job i d
ジョブIDを返してもらいます
and then we can pass this job idea
そのジョブIDを渡すことができます
as a dependency to other tasks
他のタスクへの依存関係として
for jobs as you can see what running
ご覧のように、ジョブを実行しています
jobs in the workforce with the dependency
依存関係を持つワークフローの中で
once the entire workflow is complete we can check the results.
ワークフロー全体が完了したら、結果を確認できます。
And is you can see what have our extra fishing value back.
ご覧のように、期待値が返ってきています。
And we also can check all of the
また、すべての
results from each of the steps.
各ステップの結果も確認できます。
Which are also here.
こちらにも表示されています。
And that's it for the programming model section
以上で、プログラミングモデルのセクションは終わりです
in the next chapter we're going to be talking about adventural
次の章では、応用的な
gritters
アルゴリズムについて説明します